Guide to the International Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers Local #160 (Capitol Division) records, 1873-1989 IBT0089
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
International Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers Local #160 (Capitol Division) records
1873-1989
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
IBT0089
14.75 Linear Feet
These records contain the history of The Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers Local #160, North America's oldest rail labor union, before they merged with the Teamsters in 2004. Founded in 1863 and initially named the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers. It is the oldest transportation labor organization in North America having celebrated its 150th anniversary in May 2013. The records include financial documents, meeting minutes, and memorabilia dating from 1873 to 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kenneth Briers, 2018 [2018.017].
Arrangement
This collection has been organized into 5 Series: Financial Documents, Organization Documents, Organization Election Documents, Legal Documents, and Memorabilia.
Biographical / Historical
The Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and Trainmen, initially named the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, was founded in 1863 to protect the rights of locomotive engineers after three decades of abominable working conditions. It is the oldest transportation labor organization in North America having celebrated its 150th anniversary in May 2013. In 2004, the BLET merged with International Brotherhood of Teamsters and officially changed their name to the Brotherhood of the Locomotive Engineers and Trainmen.
Division 160 of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers was located in Washington D.C. From 1873 to 1989 they kept thorough documents on meetings through writing detailed meetings in minute journals and registered members.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains financial documents, meeting minutes, correspondence, election ballets/documents, original charters, divison presses, books, booklets/brochures, and information on imsurance plans for memebers. The materials date from 1873-1989. Noted record keepers are Treasurers and Secretaries Kenneth Briers and Thomas Cox. These records are the result of 100 years of division activities such as meetings, paying dues, and elections.
International Brotherhood of Teamsters; Labor unions
- Financial documents, 1873-1985; Series 1; 3.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents regarding Division 160's Finances ranging between 1873 and 1985. Documents include ledgers of receipts for member dues, records of the division's payments to the BLE, and Treasurers reports of expenses.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Journal with Dues paid, 1873-1890; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Journal of Financial records, 1894-1901; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ledger and Cash book, 1907-1914; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Division Minutes, Dues Ledger, and Finances Book, 1907-1914; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dues and Assessment Ledger, 1976; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dues and Assessment Ledger, 1977; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements & Dues and Assessments, 1978; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements & Dues and Assessments, 1979; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements & Dues and Assessments, 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements & Dues and Assessments, 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements & Dues and Assessments, 1982; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements & Dues and Assessments, 1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements & Dues and Assessments, 1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cash Receipts and Disbursements & Dues and Assessments, 1985; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Grand Lodge, 1976; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Grand Lodge, 1977; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Grand Lodge/GCA Report, 1978; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Grand Lodge/GCA Report, 1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Grand Lodge, 1980; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Grand Lodge, 1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Division Expenses, 1969-1977; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - ID Report, 1982; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - ID Report, 1983; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - ID Report, 1984; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - ID Report, 1985; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's Report, 1977; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Treasurers Report, 1978; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - General Committee of Adjustment Audits, 1974-1976; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Organization Documents, 1873-1985; Series 2; 6.25 Linear Feet
  This series includes documents pertaining to organization records of Division 160 between 1873 and 1985. Documents include meeting minutes, registry books, and organization by-laws.
  - Division Minute Book, 1873-1902; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Division Minute Book, 1902-1906; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Division Minute Book, 1915-1923; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Division Minute Book, 1923-1930; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Division Minute Book, 1951-1961; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Division Minute Book, 1961-1982; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Register of Division 160, 1893-1909; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Register of Division 160, 1909-1919; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Register of Division 160, 1925-1944; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bowie Maryland Registration Book, 1963-1980; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Applications for Membership or Reinstatement, Undated, Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of 1978 Meeting, The Eastern Union Meeting Association Program Supplement, Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Call to Action" Letters by Kenneth Briers, 1985; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Newsletter, 1978; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Political Letters, 1976; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - By-Laws of the General Committee of Adjustment of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers on the Pennsylvania Railroad East of Pittsburgh and Erie, 1921; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws of Locomotive Engineers' Mutual Health Association of Capital Division 160 B.L.E., 1918-1919; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Locomotive Engineers Mutual Life and Accident Insurance Association, 1975-1978; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Protect Your Rights When Injury Strikes, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Regulations and Rates of Pay for the Government of Yard Enginemen Trainmen and Firemen Employed on the Washington Terminal Railroad, 1918-1919; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Ritual and Funeral Service, 1956; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Ritual and Funeral Service, 1962; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Small Address Book, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - The Pennsylvania Railroad Interpretations of Schedule Rules, 1928; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - General Wage and Rule Agreements. Decisions, Awards, and Orders, 1941; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Charter, 1905; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Charter, Undated; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Organization Election Documents, 1937-1985; Series 3; 1.50 Linear Feet
  This series includes election materials for Division 160 between 1937 and 1985. Documents includes used division ballots, election results, and national election ballots.
  - Ballots for Division 160 election, 1967; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Ballots for Division 160 election, 1971-1972; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Division 160, Official Ballot, 1973-1974; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Division 160, Official Ballot, 1976-1977; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Elections, 1976-1977; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Elections, 1979-1980; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Election, 1982; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Election 1982 Envelopes, Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Election - Local Chair, 1983; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Elections, 1985; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Recall of John F. Sytsma, 1984; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from John F. Sytsma, 1984; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Blank ballots, Undated; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Legal Documents, 1918-1986; Series 4; 1.50 Linear Feet
  This series includes legal Documents for members between 1918 and 1986. Documents include information on the Union insurance plan.
  These documents are arranged chronologically.
  - LEML & AIA Collections, 1978; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - LEML & AIA Collections, 1979; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - LEML & AIA Correspondence, 1981-1986; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - LEML & AIA Correspondence, 1981-1986; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - LEML & AIA, 1980; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - LEML & AIA, 1981-1985; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Representation Forms & Correspondence, 1985; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Health and Accident Claims, First or Formal notices, H&A Ins., 1966-1977; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Hours of Service Laws, 1969; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from General Chairman J.M. McCormick, 1937; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Insurance Collectors Copy, 1977; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Railroad Retirement Tax Forms and Rate Book, 1966-1977; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Adult Class 'A', Undated; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Juvenile, 1954; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Health & Accident, Undated; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Family Group Hospital, Undated; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Mortgage Cancellation, Undated; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - The Locomotive Engineers Investment in Florida Real Estate, 1929; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Memorabilia, 1963-1976; Series 5; 2.75 Linear Feet
  This series includes memorabilia dating between 1963 and 1976. Objects include ribbons, an inscribed bible, staming press, and magazines.
  These documents are arranged by type.
  - Stamping Press, Undated; Series 5 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Stamping Press, Undated; Series 5 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - BLE Insignia, Undated; Series 5 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Wooden Box, Undated; Series 5 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Organization Ribbon, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Inscribed Bible, Undated; Series 5 (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen 75th anniversary, 1976; Series 5 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen & Enginemen's Magazine, 1963; Series 5 (Box 22, Folder 2)